




	
	
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Predicate Logic Translations on CIS 301 Textbook</title>
    <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/5-chapter/index.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Predicate Logic Translations on CIS 301 Textbook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:05 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/5-chapter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Motivation</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/5-chapter/5_1-motivation/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/5-chapter/5_1-motivation/index.html</guid>
      <description>In this chapter, we will learn to further decompose statements in terms of their verbs (called predicates) and their nouns (called individuals). This leads to predicate logic (also called first-order logic).
As a motivation of why we want more expressive power, suppose we wanted to translate the following statements to propositional logic:
All humans are mortal. Socrates is a human. Socrates is mortal.Unfortunately, each statement would be a propositional atom:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Syntax</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/5-chapter/5_2-predsyntax/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/5-chapter/5_2-predsyntax/index.html</guid>
      <description>In this section, we will examine the syntax for translating English sentences to predicate logic. We will still create propositions (statements that are either true or false) using logical connectives (∧, ∨, →, and ¬), but now we will identify the following from our English sentences
predicates: these will be the verbs in the sentences individuals: these will be the nouns in the sentences quantifiers: these will help us specify if we mean all individuals or at least one individualDomains Predicate logic involves expressing truth about a set of individuals.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single Quantifier</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/5-chapter/5_3-singlequantifier/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/5-chapter/5_3-singlequantifier/index.html</guid>
      <description>In this section, we will see how to translate simpler statements between English to predicate logic. These translations will involve a single quantifier.
Example: Predicate logic to English Suppose our domain is animals and that we have the following two predicates:
isMouse(x): whether animal x is a mouse inHouse(x): whether animal x is in the house Suppose we also have that Squeaky is an individual in our domain.
We will practice translating from predicate logic to English.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Quantifiers</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/5-chapter/5_4-multquant/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/5-chapter/5_4-multquant/index.html</guid>
      <description>Translations that involve more than one quantifier (which often happens when some of the predicates have more than one parameter) are more challenging. We will divide these translations into two categories:
Translations that involve several of the same quantifier (multiple universal quantifiers or multiple existential quantifiers) Translations that mix quantifiers In many of the sections, we will using the predicates below (which are over the domain of shapes):
isCircle(x) - whether shape x is a circle isSquare(x) - whether shape x is a square isRectangle(x) - whether shape x is a rectangle biggerThan(x, y) - whether shape x is bigger than shape y Several of the same quantifier First, we consider translations that involve several of the same quantifier.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>