<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>




	
	
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			
			

	
	
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

	
	
			
			

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Basics and Logic Puzzles on CIS 301 Textbook</title>
    <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/1-chapter/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Basics and Logic Puzzles on CIS 301 Textbook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:05 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/1-chapter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Basic Logical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/1-chapter/1_1-logicbasics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/1-chapter/1_1-logicbasics/</guid>
      <description>What is logical reasoning? Logical reasoning is an analysis of an argument according to a set of rules. In this course, we will be learning several sets of rules for more formal anlaysis, but for now we will informally analyze English sentences and logic puzzles. This will help us practice the careful and rigorous thinking that we will need in formal proofs and in computer science in general.
Premises and conclusions A premise is a piece of information that we are given in a logical argument.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knights and Knaves</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/1-chapter/1_2-knightsknaves/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/1-chapter/1_2-knightsknaves/</guid>
      <description>We will now move to solving several kinds of logic puzzles. While these puzzles aren&amp;rsquo;t strictly necessary to understand the remaining course content, they require the same rigorous analysis that we will use when doing more formal truth tables and proofs. Plus, they&amp;rsquo;re fun!
The puzzles in this section and the rest of this chapter are all either from or inspired by: What is the Name of This Book?, by Raymond Smullyan.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Other Puzzles</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/1-chapter/1_3-otherpuzzles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis301/1-chapter/1_3-otherpuzzles/</guid>
      <description>We will look at a variety of other logic puzzles, each of which involve some statements being false and some statements being true.
Lion and Unicorn The setup for a Lion and Unicorn puzzle can vary, but the idea is that both Lion and Unicorn have specific days that they tell only lies, and other specific days that they only tell the truth.
Here is one example:
Lion always lies on Mondays, Tuesdays, and Wednesdays.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>